A Guide to the Papers of the History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia Project, 1942-2011
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia Project 1942-2011
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-46
3 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 41 folders; 1 box 5" x 6.5" x 12" with 25 DVDs; total 1.75 feet
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The files were collected by Historical Collections staff members and M.C. Wilhelm.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 2006 Morton C. (M.C.) Wilhelm, a retired UVa surgeon, was working in the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library Historical Collections, writing a biography of a prominent cancer physician. He, together with Joan Echtenkamp Klein, Curator for Historical Collections, began to reflect on the cancer program at the University of Virginia and how many individuals had played significant roles in its development over the years. M.C. and Joan then realized that many of their friends and colleagues in this group had died and, except for scattered references, their contributions to the cancer program at UVa were not recorded. Discussions with others about this lack of a historical record led to the formation of a committee to explore the possibility of writing a book which would describe the evolution of the treatment of cancer at UVa over the years. The members of the committee were a brain trust of UVa's stellar surgeons, physicians, researchers, and nurses in the field of cancer care.
In the process of acquiring material and information for the 200 page book, The History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia, 1901-2011, video-recorded interviews were conducted with 25 individuals who contributed to cancer care at UVa. These interviews are on a DVD included with each book. The book is unique in that it tells the UVa story, but it also sets the UVa history within the broader context of what was happening with cancer care in the nation and the state. A Historical Collections website incorporates the interviews and portions of the book.
Scope and Content
This collection contains documents and notes used to write The History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia, 1901-2011 by Morton C. Wilhelm and Henry K. Sharp. Included are copies of articles concerning cancer from non UVa related publications as well as those associated with UVa, such as UVa Alumni Bulletin, UVa Medical Alumni News Letter, Helix, Link, Oncologue and The Drawsheet; books notes; timelines; original reports by members of the committee on various topics such as gynecologic oncology and head and neck cancer treatment; selections and notes taken from manuscript collections in both Historical Collections and UVa's Special Collections; and 25 DVDs of video-recorded interviews.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically. Some of the folders are grouped so that all of the reports by committee members are together in a reports section. Articles photocopied from Historical Collection's UVa related journals at the beginning of the project are grouped by subject and also chronologically.
Contents List
- Book notes (not Historical Collections) n.d., Photocopies and AN (Box-folder 001-001)
  Notes are from books not housed in Historical Collections.
- Cancer project correspondence and documents 2007-2011, Photocopies of TD (Box-folder 001-002)
  Includes minutes of meetings, letters to committee members, letters to potential interviewees, DVD Reception remarks, press release, and Medical Center Hour document.
- Draft: "A History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia, 1901-2005" by Morton C. Wilhelm, M.D. [and] Henry K. Sharp, Ph.D." 2011, 1 TD (Box-folder 001-003)
  The rest of the title page draft states: Editor and Introduction by Victoria N. Meyer, Ph.D., Forward by Morton C. Wilhelm, M.D. and Joan Echtenkamp Klein, M.S.L.S., Conclusion by George A. Beller, M.D. and Peyton T. Taylor, Jr., M.S., M.D. In Collaboration with Joan Echtenkamp Klein, M.S.L.S., Janet S. Pearson, M.L.S., Sonya Coleman, B.S. Historical Collections Claude Moore Health Sciences Library University of Virginia Copyright 2011 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia
- Cancer project notes of DVDs of interviewees n.d., 21 sets of AN and typed notes (Box-folder 001-004)
  M.C. Wilhelm made notes while listening to the audio tapes of Robert W. Cantrell, M.D.; David Cattell-Gordon, M.S.W.; Jay Y. Gillenwater, M.D.; Gerald Goldstein, M.D.; Kenneth E. Greer, M.D.; Sharon L. Hostler, M.D.; John A. Jane, Sr., M.D., Ph.D.; Theodore E. Keats, M.D.; James M. Larner, M.D.; Robert E. McLaughlin, M.D.; Stacey E. Mills, M.D.; Daniel N. Mohler, M.D.; Mary Jane Morris, R.N.; J. Thomas Parsons, Ph.D.; Bradley M. Rodgers, M.D.; Craig L. Slingluff, M.D.; Peyton T. Taylor, Jr., M.D.; Michael J. Weber, Ph.D.; Munsey S. Wheby, M.D.; and Michael E. Williams, M.D. Scott Jones, M.D. was not taped, but included in this folder are notes that Dr. Wilhelm made following a conversation. The actual DVDs are stored in Box 4.
- Historical Collection Articles 1942-2002, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-005)
  Articles are predominantly from UVa Med Alum News Letter, The Draw Sheet, Helix, Link, and Inside UVA.
- Historical Collection Articles: Basic Science varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-006)
  Includes a report by Byrd Leavell on the Hematology Division.
- Historical Collection Articles: Cancer Center Administration varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-007)
  Includes a draft of a paper by Tom O'Leary.
- Historical Collection Articles: Dermatology varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-008)
  Includes additional departmental papers.
- Historical Collection Articles: Education varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-009)
- Historical Collection Articles: Gynecologic Oncology varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-010)
- Historical Collection Articles: Medical Oncology varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 001-011)
- Historical Collection Articles: Otolaryngology varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 002-001)
- Historical Collection Articles: Pediatrics varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 002-002)
- Historical Collection Articles: Radiology varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 002-003)
- Historical Collection Articles: Surgery varied, Photocopies of journal articles, journals, AN, slides (Box-folder 002-004)
  Additional documents and articles contributed by M.C. Wilhlem: a paper, "Ourselves and Patients Who Are Dying" by Lockhart B. Mcguire; "Pancreatic Cancer Resection Outcome in American University Centers in 1989-1990" with Morton C. Wilhelm as the last author; an issue of Behavioral Medicine with an article titled "The Relationship Between Psychosocial Factors and Breast Cancer: Some Unexpected Results" by Jeffrey R. Edwards, Carl L. Cooper, S. Gail Pearl, Ellen S. de Paredes, Tom O'Leary, and Morton C. Wilhelm; an issue of Link; 6 issues of Oncologue; slides of an approved hospital cancer program; American College of Surgeons Commission on Cancer Task Force Reports; "Technique and Guidelines for Needle Localization Biopsy of Nonpalpable Lesions of the Breast" by M. C. Wilhelm and H. J. Wanebo; "Evolution of the Clinical Experience of Thyroid Cancer at the University of Virginia 1982-2002" by Tom Daniel with notes by M.C. Wilhelm; "A New Look at Lung Cancer" by George Minor with notes by M.C. Wilhelm.
- Historical Collection Articles: Urology varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 002-005)
- Historical Collections: Book Notes and Books/Papers varied, Photocopies of TD, 1 paper (Box-folder 002-006)
  Includes The Early Years of The University of Virginia Hospital: An Analysis of Patient's Records by Wilhelm Moll and Todd L. Savitt; History of the Out-Patient Department, University of Virginia Hospital by Alice E. Smith, excerpts from several Report of Activities by the Virginia Cancer Foundation, Inc., and History of the Medical Department of the University of Virginia, 1825-1914 by John S. Davis; notes taken from the History of the Paul Goodloe McIntire Memorial Clinic at the University of Virginia Hospital by Zula Mae Baber and The Dedication Exercises of the New Buildings of the Department of Medicine of the University of Virginia; and photocopied title pages of books consulted.
- Historical Collections Manuscript Collection: Albemarle County Medical Society varied, Photocopies of articles, TD, and reports (Box-folder 002-007)
  Includes "The Physician's Role in an Albemarle County Medical Society Program for Early Cancer Detection" and reports and minutes of the Bessie Dunn Miller Clinic for Cancer Prevention.
- Historical Collections Manuscript Collection: Papers of Dr. Edward Watson Hook varied, Photocopies of TD (Box-folder 002-008)
  Includes papers by Byrd Leavell on the Hematology Division and the Medical Oncology Division as well as papers from the Cancer Studies Division with documents related to the Booz, Allen & Hamilton study.
- Historical Collections Manuscript Collection: Hospital Executive Director's Office (HEDO) varied, Photocopies of TL, TD (Box-folder 002-009)
  Includes letters and minutes of meetings related to the Bessie Dunn Miller Clinic, costs for Virginia Cancer Foundation patients, the Tumor Clinic, conflict between the Department of Roentgenology and Department of Neurological Surgery, a proposed hospital for terminal cancer patients, "Minimum Requirements for Approval of a Cancer Program" paper, the Cancer Registry, Long-Range Planning Committee meetings including reports on a UVa Cancer Center.
- Historical Collections Manuscript Collection: Papers of the UVa Medical Alumni Association varied, Photocopies of TD (Box-folder 002-010)
  Includes an interview with Vincent Archer, typescripts of speeches by Harvey E. Jordan and John L. Newcomb, a "Report of Meeting of the Medical Alumni Committee, April, 1940," and documents from the University of Virginia Development Fund including a 1948 "Report of the Medical School and Hospital."
- Historical Collections Manuscript Collections varied, Photocopies of TD and AN (Box-folder 002-011)
  Includes notes taken from the Papers of Armistead Page Booker, School of Medicine Student Notebooks, Hospital Record Books, University of Virginia Hospital Auxiliary Collection, Miscellaneous Letters and Documents Collection, and the Papers of the University of Virginia Hospital Isotope and Radiation Hazards Committee.
- A History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia, 1901-2011 proof 2011, Proof (Box-folder 002-012)
  This is the last proof set sent back to Historical Collections from DEStech. Pages where more errors were found were sent back to DEStech after a photocopy was made and inserted into this proof set.
- Journal Articles - Non UVA Publications varied, Photocopies of journal articles (Box-folder 003-001)
  Includes non UVa articles referenced in A History of Cancer Care at the University of Virginia. See also Virginia Health Bulletin folder in Box 3, Folder 15.
- Miscellaneous varied, Photocopies TD and AN, brochure (Box-folder 003-002)
  Includes various notes; a Bibliography of the History of the University of Virginia Hospital based on the Health Sciences Library, Special Collections, Law Library, and the Fine Arts Library; and a Report of the Cancer Center brochure with statistical data from 1996.
- Report: Cancer Center Administration by Tom O'Leary n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-003)
- Report: Cancer Center Education, Support and Outreach by Diane Cole n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-004)
- Report: Gynecologic Oncology by Peyton T. Taylor n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-005)
- Report: Medical Oncology by Gerald Goldstein n.d., TD and AN (Box-folder 003-005)
- Report: Neurosurgical Oncology by John A. Jane, Sr. 2007 August 28, TD (Box-folder 003-007)
- Report: Otolaryngology by Robert W. Cantrell n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-008)
- Report: Pathology by David E. Smith 2008 August 12, TD (Box-folder 003-009)
- Report: Pediatrics by Sharon Hostler n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-010)
- Report: Surgery by M.C. Wilhelm n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-011)
- Report: Urology by Jay Gillenwater n.d., TD (Box-folder 003-012)
- Special Collection Notes by Henry Sharp varied, Photocopies of TD, AN (Box-folder 003-013)
  Includes notes taken from the Virginia Medical Monthly, the Papers of the University of Virginia President, Annual Reports to the President, Correspondence of Charles Pinckney Jones, and Letterbooks of the Official Correspondence of the University of Virginia Faculty Chairman.
- Timelines: National Cancer Institute, American Cancer Society, University of Virginia Hospital, University of Virginia School of Medicine varied, Photocopy of journal article, TD, booklet (Box-folder 003-014)
  Includes Cancer Control Through the Years 1913-1980: A narrative outline of voluntary cancer control programs -- nationally and in Virginia by Bernard W. Woodahl.
- UVa Cancer Registry Annual Distribution Report 2000-2007, TD (Box-folder 003-015)
  New cancer cases: Distribution by sex, class, and AJCC stage at diagnosis.
- University of Virginia Bulletins varied, Photocopies of articles (Box-folder 003-016)
  The name of the publication changed over time and includes The Alumni Bulletin, Bulletins of the University of Virginia, and Alumni Bulletin of the University of Virginia.
- University of Virginia Alumni News varied, Photocopies of articles, AN (Box-folder 003-017)
- Virginia Health Bulletin varied, Photocopies of articles (Box-folder 003-018)
- >Letter from Steven T. DeKosky to Henry K. Sharp, 2011 March 23, 1 TLS, envelope (Box-folder 003-019)
- Emily Couric Cancer Care Center Factoids n.d., 1TD (Box-folder 003-020)
  The factoids concern the construction of the ECCCC, mainly how much electrical wire, glass, rebar, etc.
- Cancer project DVDs of interviewees 2008-2010, 25 DVDs (Box-folder 004-000)
  Interviewees are Robert W. Cantrell, M.D.; David Cattell-Gordon, M.S.W.; Diane D. Cole, M.P.H.; Milton T. Edgerton, M.D.; Jay Y. Gillenwater, M.D.; Gerald Goldstein, M.D.; Kenneth E. Greer, M.D.; Sharon L. Hostler, M.D.; John A. Jane, Sr., M.D., Ph.D.; Theodore E. Keats, M.D.; James M. Larner, M.D.; Robert E. McLaughlin, M.D.; Stacey E. Mills, M.D.; Daniel N. Mohler, M.D.; Mary Jane Morris, R.N.; Thomas J. O'Leary, Ph.D.; J. Thomas Parsons, Ph.D.; Bradley M. Rodgers, M.D.; Craig L. Slingluff, M.D.; Peyton T. Taylor, Jr., M.D.; Agathe van der Erve, R.N.; Michael J. Weber, Ph.D.; Munsey S. Wheby, M.D.; Morton C. Wilhelm, M.D.; and Michael E. Williams, M.D.